<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strange and wonderful news from Italy, or, A true amd impartial relation of the travels, adventures, and martyrdome of four eminent Quakers of York-shire who in the year 1672 travelled through France, Italy, and Turkey to propagate their religion : wherein is fully and faithfully declared the deigns, endeavours, and attempts of these zealous Quakers for the conversion of the Turk and Pope : with a summary account of the event and success of the business and of all the most remarkable occurrents : as also a faithful narrative of their private discourses, conferences, and disputes which passed between these Quakers and the Pope, the Cardinal Nephew, and Cardinal Barbarini : also of their voyage to Constantinople and of their most barbarous, cruel, and bloody death by the special command of the Mufti and the Vizier Bassa / faithfully and compendiously related by Elias Wilson.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Elias.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2891A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26383</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09448049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09448049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1320:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strange and wonderful news from Italy, or, A true amd impartial relation of the travels, adventures, and martyrdome of four eminent Quakers of York-shire who in the year 1672 travelled through France, Italy, and Turkey to propagate their religion : wherein is fully and faithfully declared the deigns, endeavours, and attempts of these zealous Quakers for the conversion of the Turk and Pope : with a summary account of the event and success of the business and of all the most remarkable occurrents : as also a faithful narrative of their private discourses, conferences, and disputes which passed between these Quakers and the Pope, the Cardinal Nephew, and Cardinal Barbarini : also of their voyage to Constantinople and of their most barbarous, cruel, and bloody death by the special command of the Mufti and the Vizier Bassa / faithfully and compendiously related by Elias Wilson.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, Elias.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Lock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Europe --  History.</term>
               <term>Christian martyrs --  Turkey.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43130:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43130:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Strange and Wonderful News from ITALY, OR, A True and Impartial Relation of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, Adventures, and Martyrdome of four emient Quakers of York-ſhire.</p>
            <p>Who in the Year 1672. Travelled through <hi>France, Italy</hi> and <hi>Turky</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate their Religion.</p>
            <p>Wherein is fully and faithfully declared the Deſigns, Endeavours and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of theſe zealous <hi>Quakers</hi> for the Converſion of the TURK and POPE.</p>
            <p>With a ſummary account of the event and ſucceſs of the buſineſs, and of all the moſt remarkable occurrents. As alſo a faithful Narrative of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſcourſes, conferences and diſputes which paſſed between theſe <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Cardinal Nephew</hi> and <hi>Cardinal Barbarini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO Of their Voyage to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and of their moſt barbarous, cruel and bloody death by the ſpecial command of the <hi>Mufti</hi> and the <hi>Vizier Baſſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully and compendiouſly related by <hi>Elias Wilſon</hi> Eſquire, who was an eye-witneſs to a great part of theſe tranſactions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Lock,</hi> living in the <hi>Long Walk</hi> near <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Hoſpital, over againſt the ſign of the Drawers. 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43130:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IT was towards the end of <hi>March</hi> in the year 1672. that <hi>John Watſon, William Stubbs, Nathaniel Golden,</hi> and <hi>Rowland Jenkins,</hi> all of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and eminently known in that County to be <hi>Leading-men</hi> among the <hi>Quakers:</hi> It was <hi>I</hi> ſay, about that time that theſe men ſaid they had the <hi>ſpirit of Burning</hi> and the <hi>Holy Anointing</hi> in them, and were called and ſent by God to preach the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Heathens.</hi> And they ſaid that the <hi>child Jeſus</hi> within them had aſſured them of great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and that the Lord would be wonderfully with them in this <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> that they ſhould break the <hi>Bread of Life</hi> to the Nations, and that the <hi>Springs of Life</hi> ſhould break forth out of their Bellies. It is a wonder to fee what ſtrange effects and boldneſs theſe <hi>Enthuſiaſtical perſwaſions</hi> and <hi>Phanatical Dreams</hi> cauſed in theſe poor Men. They were now ſwelled with hopes and expectation of Wonders. They now reſolved to leave <hi>England</hi> and embark for <hi>France,</hi> and begin this <hi>great work</hi> of converting <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader, I</hi> do intend to give you a true and impartial account of theſe mens actions in Forreign parts, as <hi>I</hi> have received it from their own mouths, and alſo been fully and faithfully informed by ſeveral other Perſons of known worth and integrity, who were eye witneſſes to the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Watſon</hi> was a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of a pretty conſiderable Eſtate, and had been well educated, he had ſpent ſome years at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> and had alſo formerly been a Traveller into <hi>France, Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> all which Languages he throughly underſtood, and ſpake very fluently. The other three were plain Country-men, and knew no other language but their own, but fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves they ſhould have the <hi>Gift of Tongues,</hi> and be indued with power from above.</p>
            <p>It is not my intent to write a <hi>Journal</hi> of theſe mens actions, for that would ſwell this little Pamphlet into a huge book. <hi>I</hi> intend only to relate ſome of the moſt ſignal and moſt remarkable of their affairs and tranſactions, which <hi>I</hi> heard from their own mouths when <hi>I</hi> was in <hi>Italy,</hi> and which have been alſo related and atteſted by other Perſons of known integrity.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Eaſter-week</hi> they took Shipping at <hi>Dover,</hi> and were ſoon wafted over to <hi>Calis. I</hi> find not that they had any Impulſe of Spirit to ſay or attempt any thing, but that they travelled on very peaceably and quietly, paying for what they had, and ſo came to the great City <hi>Paris,</hi> where they ſpent 2 days only and then advanced towards <hi>Lyons,</hi> where they continued about a Fortnight. Here it was that the tumultuous ſpirit began firſt to exert and ſhew it ſelf to the <hi>French Nation.</hi> On <hi>April</hi> 27 <hi>William Stubbs</hi> ſaid he had received a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God to ſpeak; and he ſignified as much to <hi>John Watſon</hi> and the reſt On the next day which was Sunday, about 10 of the Clock in the Forenoon they went all 4 to the great <hi>Cathedral,</hi> or St. <hi>Johns Church,</hi> where they were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43130:2"/>celebrating <hi>high Maſs</hi> (as they call it) about the middle of the <hi>Maſs William Stubbs</hi> on a ſudden climes over the ralls and goes up to the high Altar, where as he was beginning his Diſcourſe in <hi>Engliſh</hi> (for as yet he had not received his <hi>Gift of Tongues</hi>) the <hi>Church Officers</hi> preſently lay hands on him and carry him out, and commit him to Priſon until the next day. On <hi>Monday</hi> the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers have him before the Magiſtrate, who refuſes to meddle in this caſe, but cauſes him forthwith to be ſent to the Arch-Biſhop. The Arch-Biſhop is highly offended with him for his bold attempt, and reſolves to puniſh him with all ſeverity imaginable, he remits him to Priſon, and orders that the next day at 10 of the Clock in the Morning, he be brought before him again. On <hi>Tueſday</hi> he is ſtrictly examined what his intentions were, &amp; how he durſt be ſo bold to commit ſo great a crime in ſo publick and confident a manner; His anſwers were altogether impertinent, and withall ſo inſolent and ſawcy, that the Biſhop ſent him to the <hi>Houſe of Correction</hi> where he was ſoundly laſhed. On <hi>Friday</hi> morning the Biſhop ordered him to be brought before him again; and ſeemed to be much incenſed againſt this poor <hi>Phanatick,</hi> Now the reaſon why his <hi>Grace</hi> was ſo fierce againſt this poor Man was, becauſe ſome of his Servants had malitiouſly ſuggeſted to him that he was ſet on and encouraged to offer this publick affront to their Divine Service by ſome of the <hi>Hugonot Miniſters:</hi> which was a moſt malitious untruth, for as yet theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> had not had any the leaſt correſpondence or converſe with any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant in <hi>France,</hi> as they did all very ſoberly atteſt to me in <hi>Italy.</hi> The Biſhop was reſolved to give him a full hearing, and to ſift the buſineſs to the bottom. He asked him if he was not ſet on to do this irreverent action by the <hi>Hugonot Miniſters?</hi> He replyed no, he was moved by the Spirit of God within him, and that it was the <hi>Spirit of Burning</hi> and the <hi>Holy Anointing</hi> that had cauſed him to do what he had done. And here he entred into a long diſcourſe, telling the <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> and the <hi>Canons</hi> who were there preſent, that the Law of God was written upon Mens hearts, and that now the time was come that they ſhould all be taught of God: Now the Lords people were all to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, they were all to have freſh ſprings ariſe in their hearts. And that the Lord had ſent him and three Friends more into theſe parts to break the bread of Life to the Nations, to open the hidden Myſteries of Chriſts Kingdom, to overthrow the <hi>Babyloniſh Practices</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to break the Serpents Head, and wound the great <hi>Leviathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arch-Biſhop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the <hi>Canons,</hi> and the whole Company were much aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at this Mans confidence, and his wild and Fanatick diſcourſe and an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwers, and began now to relent, and to pitty this poor Man, and look upon him as a mad-man and one out of his ſenſes, &amp; ſo accordingly gave order to have him to the Hoſpital of <hi>mad people,</hi> and there carefully to be looked after until he gave further order.</p>
            <p>About a week after this, 3 <hi>Engliſh Gentlemen</hi> hearing what had paſſed, and how that an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> who was mad was committed to the Hoſpital of <hi>mad
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43130:3"/>men:</hi> The Genttlemen went immediately to the Hoſpital to enquire the truth of the matter, when they came the Keeper very courteouſly informed them of the whole buſineſs, brought them to the ſight of <hi>Stubbs;</hi> who was locked up in a ſmall Cell by himſelf alone, and an iron Chain about his Leg, and his head ſhaved, (for it is the cuſtome here to ſhave all mad people.) When the Gentlemen came in they found him ſitting in a melancholly ſullen poſtuee: he would not ſo much as look up or ſpeak one word to them for the ſpace of above an hour and half, notwithſtanding they ſpoke very kindly to him, and asked him concerning his condition, and the cauſes of his diſtemper, and promiſed him all the aſſiſtance &amp; kindneſs that lay in their power. At laſt this ſullen Spirit was overcome, and he began to enter into a long diſcourſe of the ſpirit within him, and that God had ſent him and his 3 Friends to break in pieces the great <hi>Leviathan</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now the Gentlemen quickly perceived his Spirit, and plainly diſcovered him to be no <hi>mad-man</hi> but a <hi>Quaker.</hi> They asked him concerning his other Friends where they were? And withall promiſed to do their utmoſt for his releaſment, and ſo giving the Keeper ſome Money to be kind to their Country-man they bid him farewel. At Evening they went to the Inn to vifit the other 3 <hi>Quakers,</hi> and had much diſcourſe with them, endeavouring to perſwade them to deſiſt from this ſo hazardous and fruitleſs an enterprize, and ſpeedily to return to their own Country, demonſtrating the great dangers and inconveniences they would thruſt themſelves upon if they did ſtill perſiſt or any farther proſecute this fond and ridiculous undertaking; and ſo they parted. The next day they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed to the Arch-Biſhop, who was pleaſed to entertain them with much ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and reſpect. They returned humble thanks to his <hi>Grace</hi> for his great care of their Country-man, in ſending him to ſuch a place where he was ſo well accommodated in all thing in order to his cure, and withall repreſented to his Grace his condition, quality and Religion; and how that he was not a <hi>mad-man</hi> but one of thoſe <hi>Sectarians</hi> which in <hi>England</hi> are called <hi>Pha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aticks</hi> and <hi>Quakers.</hi> And withall informed the Arch-Biſhop and Canons how that party do deſire to appear different from all others in their manner of ſpeech, their apparel, and manners. And alſo humbly petitioned his Grace for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſment, promiſing within a day or two to diſpatch them out of the Town; The Arch-Biſhop-readily condeſcended to all their demands, and preſently gave order that <hi>Stubbs</hi> ſhould be ſet at liberty, which was accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And the day following they all 4 left the Town, and haſted their Journey to <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they came to <hi>Milano</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> they had another enthuſiaſtical im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of Spirit. And now <hi>John Watſon, Nathaniel Golden</hi> and <hi>Rowland Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> who hitherto had been ſilent, or (as they expreſſed it themſelves) <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly waiting at the Feet of Jeſus,</hi> who had now given them command to begin to preach the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>Italians.</hi> Here <hi>Stubbs</hi> accompanied with his 3 friends did now (as formerly at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France</hi>) upon <hi>Sunday</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43130:3"/>enter the <hi>Domo</hi> or <hi>Cathedral</hi> of the City, and made a great and publick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance when they were in the height of their ſolemnities. <hi>Watſon</hi> began to make a diſcourſe in <hi>Italian,</hi> but was preſently ſeized and carried forth, and had before a Magiſtrate, who forthwith committed them all 4 to Priſon, but withall gave order they ſhould be civilly uſed and lack for nothing until fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order, About 4 or 5 days after, they were commanded to appear before the <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> himſelf who was reſolved to have a full account of the matter, The Governour when he ſaw their uncivil behaviour, their ſullen looks, and heard their wild diſcourſes, he preſently concluded them <hi>mad-men,</hi> and gave order to have them confined and carefully looked after, and alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed 2 Phyſitians to viſit them and to do their utmoſt for their recovery. The Phyſitians preſently made a viſit to the Hoſpital and had a long diſcourſe with <hi>Watſon</hi> (who ſpoke <hi>Italian</hi> well) And then returned to the Governour to give him their ſentiment of the buſineſs, they told his Excellence that they were mad, as did evidently appear to them by their very countenance and manner of diſcourſe: and that one of them (meaning <hi>Stubbs</hi>) had a manifeſt and ſignal token of his diſtemper, <hi>viz.</hi> his head was ſhaved according to the uſual practice of all Phyſitians in the World, who always uſe to ſhave mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereby to cool the brain, and for the more comodious applying fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and other proper Remedies for the Head, the ſeat and ſubject of the diſtemper. They added alſo that they did verily believe they were <hi>Dutch-men</hi> who had made an eſcape from their Keepers. The Governour was well ſatiſfied with this account the Phyſitians gave of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordered them to take care of them, and let no means be wanting, that might be uſed for their recovery, and that they ſhould be uſed with all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs imaginable. The 2 Doctors return to the <hi>Pazzi</hi> or <hi>mad-men,</hi> and cauſe them to be ſhaved and purged, and the next day they bleed them all in the arms &amp; feet; &amp; every day twice a day cauſe their heads to be bathed with cold water, and their whole bodies alſo in a pond made for that uſe only. Here the poor <hi>Quakers</hi> went through a rigorous courſe of Phyſick: for in a months time they were let blood about 17 or 18 ſeveral times, beſides fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and violent purgings. <hi>Golden</hi> a fortnight after he had been thus confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, forbore eating, whether it was out of a ſullen dogged humour, or out of an enthuſiaſme or expectation of <hi>new Revelations, I</hi> cannot certainly affirm, but by his wilfull and contumacious abſtinence he gave up the Ghoſt and died after he had been a month thus ſhut up. The other 3 by bleeding and purging were brought very low, the Phyſitians now were much troubled &amp; diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and did altogether deſpair of their recovery, and did ſignifie as much to the Governour withall telling his Excellence that they ſuppoſed it was ſome <hi>Religious melancholly</hi> that theſe men were afflicted with, &amp; that it was inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable &amp; not to be overcome by any Art, &amp; ſo deſired the Governour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe them, which was accordingly performed. After they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained their liberty, they continued ſome days in the Town,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43130:4"/>and would frequently make ſpeeches in the Churches, and exhort the people to imbrace their Doctrine and follow the Light which was within them. The <hi>Italians</hi> after their enlargement were very civil to them, and if at any time they cauſed any diſturbance in the Church, the Officers would gently force them out, without uſing any manner of rigour or ſeverity to them. For the whole City looked upon them as 3 diſtracted men, ſo whatſoever they ſaid or did was looked upon, as proceeding from the Diſtemper of their brain, and civilly connived at and paſſed over without any notice.</p>
            <p>Towards the beginning of <hi>June</hi> they left <hi>Milano</hi> and ſet forward for <hi>Rome.</hi> For their chief deſign was to go thither, to convert the <hi>great Leviathan</hi> (as they uſually called the <hi>Pope</hi>) and to reform <hi>Babilon. I</hi> heard not of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable action in their Journey from <hi>Milan</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi> but you may imagine by their bald Sculls and moroſe carriage what thoughts the people had of them, for now whereſoever they came the people looked upon them as men diſtracted and mad: ſome were afraid of them, others laughed at and derided them, no body at all regarded any thing they ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 18 they came to <hi>Rome</hi> the place they ſo much deſired to ſee, upon the <hi>Sunday</hi> following they according to their old Cuſtome entred a little Church called <hi>San Jacomo Scozza Cavaelli,</hi> where <hi>Watſon</hi> made a fierce and zealous diſcourſe againſt the <hi>Babiloniſh Idolatry</hi> of that City, and ſaid that the <hi>Pope</hi> who was the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> and the <hi>great Leviathan</hi> was now to be cruſhed in pieces, and God had ſent them from the utmoſt parts of the Earth to convert that City, and to confound the <hi>Pope</hi> and all his <hi>Adherents,</hi> and that now all mankind was to expect and ſeek for the <hi>holy Anointing,</hi> for they were all to be taught of God, and not any longer to follow Monks and Prieſts, who were all falſe Prophets, and that now God would pour out the full Vials of his wrath and fierce indignation upon them, and bring them all to utter ruine ſhame and confuſion. <hi>I</hi> know the Reader will admire to hear that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> were ſo patient, and let them run on ſo long in theſe diſcourſes, and not cauſe them to be carried out of the Church and puniſhed for this diſturbance. But the reaſon of this connivance was not for want of zeal, but becauſe the Church and Congregation was very ſmall, ſo that the people were affrighted and all kept at a good diſtance, for by their very looks and manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the people generally concluded them 3 Bedlams, and were greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of them, until at laſt one who had more courage and reſolution then the reſt, went and fetcht ſome Officers and put them into the inquiſition os <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> But thoſe of the inquiſition ſoon rid their hands of them, and the ſame day towards Evening ſet them at liberty, ſaying that it was their buſineſs only to take notice of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and not of <hi>mad-men.</hi> The next day which was the great ſolemnity of St, <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> they cauſed the ſame diſturbance in the great <hi>Domo,</hi> that famous and renowned Church of St, <hi>Peter,</hi> but here they were quickly carried out, but no other ſeverity uſed, becauſe all the world now looked upon them as <hi>mad-men,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43130:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>I</hi> am weary of relating theſe frantick attempts and diſcourſes which they made in ſeveral of the Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo ſhall paſs by a great many of them in ſilence, and come to their attempts upon the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf. They went to the <hi>Engliſh Colledge</hi> and deſired the Govemours aſſiſtance to bring them to the preſence of the <hi>Pope.</hi> The Governour refuſed to meddle in that matter, alledging the dangerous conſequents of it, that it would not only bring particular ruine to themſelves, but would alſo be a ſhame and reproach to the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> it ſelf: Wherefore he earneſtly prſſed and urged them to deſiſt from that dangerous attempt, and return home. Hereupon the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> fell in a great paſſion, and told him that he ſavoured not the things of God, but was yet wholly carnal, and that he was like <hi>Herod,</hi> and with him went about as much as in him lay to murder the <hi>child Jeſus,</hi> and to hinder the peoples converſion from Idolatry, and embracing the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> and ſo in great diſcontent they left him.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The conference of Cardinal Barbarini with the Engliſh Quakers, and how he brought them before the Pope.</head>
               <p>Theſe poor <hi>Quakers</hi> had not been a month in <hi>Rome</hi> but the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-took great notice of them; and generally condoled their condition, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtracted and far from their own Country, <hi>July</hi> 6 <hi>Cardinal Barbarini,</hi> hearing much of theſe mens frantick actions, was very deſirous out of curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſee them, and to diſcourſe with them, hereupon he cauſed them to be before him, and was pleaſed with much patience to diſcourſe an hour with them; and then civilly diſmiſſed them, and ſent then to their Lodgings. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two days after he made report to the <hi>Cardinal Nephew</hi> and to the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf of what had happened, and of the ſtrange and unparelleld enthuſiaſms of theſe 3 Engliſh <hi>Pazzi</hi> (for ſo he always termed them) and how they had a great deſire to have ſome conference with his Holineſs; and that they affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that God had ſent them to deliver ſome ſecret Revelations to him. The Pope at firſt was a little ſurprized with the novelty and ſtrangeneſs of he thing, and gave order to have them privately brought before him and theſe 2 Cardinals. When they were admitted into the preſence, <hi>Watſon</hi> ſaluted the Pope with this addreſs. <hi>Art thou that Man of Sin, that Antichriſt and great Leviathan, Verily God hath raiſed us up from the utmoſt parts of the earth to preach the everlaſting Goſpel to thee, and to conver thee from thy Idolatry, Errours and ſinful ways, unto the true way and to the Light, &amp;c.</hi> The Pope was much amazed at this ſtrange confidence and prodigions boldneſs, and did really believe that the common report had not at al belyed them, but that they were very much diſtempered in their minds, and diſtracted, and gave a ſtrict command that none ſhould offer any violence to them; but withall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately appointed ſome of the <hi>Engliſh Colledge</hi> to perſwade them to return home, or elſe to take charge of them in their Colle<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, and not let them thus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43130:5"/>run about the City, diſturbing the people. The buſineſs was effected accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Popes deſire, for about the end of <hi>July</hi> ſeeing how unſucceſfull their endeavours had been they reſolved to leave that <hi>Babylonian City,</hi> and go preach the Goſpel to the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahometans.</hi> In order thereunto they took Shipping for <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtantinople,</hi> where after two months toſſing upon a dangerous and tempeſtuous Sea they at length ſafely arrived.</p>
               <p>They had not been above a fortnight in that great City, but they went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Mahometans Moſco's</hi> and <hi>Temples,</hi> and cauſed great tumult among the People. For this offence t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey were condemned to be baſtinado'd, <hi>i. e,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive 300 blows upon the ſoals of their Feet, which was accordingly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the extremity of rigour and cruelty, ſo that in few days the putrified fleſh came off from the bones, which was a miſerable ſpectacle to behold, But this ſpirit of <hi>Fanaeticiſm</hi> had ſo tranſported and infatuated them, that they got wooden crutches, and once more went to their prophance <hi>Moſco's,</hi> and cauſed a much greater diſturbance then before. Hereupon the <hi>Turks</hi> were exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly incenſed, and preſently had them before the <hi>Mufti</hi> himſelf, who forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in a great fury and rage paſſed this cruel ſentence upon them, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were to have their hands chopt off, their tongues cut out, their eyes bored out, and each man to have a ſharp wooden ſtake run in at his Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſo quite through his body, all which was accordingly put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſo theſe poor wretches after all their ſufferings ended their miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Life, This raſhneſs of theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> had like to drew a great ſtorm upon all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants who were in great danger of having their Eſtates and Goods ſeized by the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> but that the <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſador</hi> nobly and notably beſtirred himſelf, and gave the <hi>Vizier Baſſa</hi> a full and ſatiſfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry account of the whole matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> in this ſhort account of theſe Mens actions, <hi>I</hi> have not ſtudied to ſet it out with eloquence and ornament, but <hi>I</hi> have wholly and only aimed at truth, reſolving to give you a true and impartial Narrative of the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. <hi>I</hi> was well acquairted with theſe Men in <hi>Italy,</hi> and had often confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with them. And of ſome things <hi>I</hi> was informed by others. As concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their actions and crue death in <hi>Turky I</hi> received a full account by Letter when <hi>I</hi> was at <hi>Venice</hi> fron two of my Friends and faithful correſpondents reſident in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who were eye-witneſſes of their cruel and moſt barbarous deaths. Whoſe Letters <hi>I</hi> have ſtill by me, and am willing and ready at any time to exhibit them to the view and peruſal of any who ſhall deſire a more full account of this matter.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43130:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
